The Lives of the Prophets Part 2;
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
The next story; is the longest story of a Nabi(نَبِي) in Qur'an.
It is the story of Al-Kaleem(ألكليم) Musa عليه الصلواة والسّلام.
Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) was mentioned in more than 30 positions or Su'ar(سورة) in Qur'an and he was mentioned 124 times.
One of the scholars said;
كاد القران ان يكون موسى
Qur'an was almost going to become the story of Musa(موسى).
The story of Musa(موسى) was mentioned so many times in Qur'an that this scholar said;
Qur'an was almost going to be the story of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); A Hundred and 24 times
There's no other Nabi(نَبِي) in Qur'an; who's mentioned more than Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
And there is no story that takes a longer space and span of Qur'an discussed in elaborate details, in many positions of Qur'an, like the story of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
Why?
Is it because he's one of the greatest Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); he's one of Uulul Azam(أولو العزم); the five strongest prophets;
which are Muhammadﷺ, Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), Musa(موسى), Eesa(عيسى) and Nuh(نوح), these are the five.
Is it because of that?
Well, Ibrahim عليه السّلام is also one of Uulul Azam(أولو العزم);
Infact Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that the opinion of the scholars is; that the best Nabi(نَبِي) after Muhammadﷺ is Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم)
but the story of Ibrahim عليه السّلام is not mentioned as frequently, it comes nowhere close to the details of the story of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
So how come this story was mentioned in so much details in Qur'an?
There's a few reasonsl; Let's go through them.
Number one; The Ummah(امة) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) are the last Muslim Ummah(امة), before the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
You know that there are many Muslim nations throughout history.
The Ummah(امة) of Nuh(نوح), the Ummah(امة)  of Adam(آدَم), the Ummah(امة) of Hud(هود), the Ummah(امة) of Saleh(صالح)
the last Ummah(امة) is the Ummah(امة) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So they are the closest in proximity to the Ummah(امة)  of Muhammadﷺ.
And since this Ummah(امة) of  Muhammadﷺ, are the inheritors of all of the former and previous messages;
it is important for us to know the Ummah(امة) that was right before us; the ones who are proceeding us.
Number two;
The history of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) is extremely rich with experiences.
It is an Ummah(امة) that lived for a long time lasted for a while, they went through a lot.
They committed a lot of mistakes.
There was a lot of misguidance there was a lot of conflicts.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted us to have all of this experience in front of our eyes;
so that we could use it in our, Da'wah(دعوة) in our long history as the Muslim Ummah(امة).
The Ummah(امة) of Musa(موسى) went through experiences;
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), they went through experiences and they committed mistakes.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى knew that Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ would fall in the same particular mistakes that Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) fell into,
and that's why it's important for us to have a history to look back to.
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
لتتبعن سنن من كان قبلكم،
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; You would follow the footsteps of the nations before you;
Step by step, inch by inch, foot by foot, even if they are going to enter into a hole of a lizard, you would follow them and do it.
The Sahabah(صحابه) said; Are you talking about the Jews and Christians.?
Rasool Ullah said; Who else.
We are going to follow the tracks.
We're going to follow their tracks, we're going to do the same thing as they did.
We're going to commit the same mistakes.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given us this wealth of information and experience so that it could be light for us; the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
Number three;
The nature of the conflict of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) is similar to the nature of the conflict of the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
With the people of Hud(هود); How were they destroyed?
Violent wind.
The people of Saleh(صالح); How were they destroyed?
By the Sieha(صيحا).
The people of Lut(لوط); How were they destroyed?
By the shaking of the earth and lifting them up and throwing them down.
So did, Hud عليه السّلام and his followers fight in Jihad(جهاد) against their people?
No.
Did Saleh(صالح) fight in Jihad(جهاد) against his people actual war?
What about with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)?
Did they fight against their enemies?
Yes.
And that's why; one of the scholar said; Since the Torah(توراة) was revealed, it was Jihad(جهاد).
It wasn't special punishments coming from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى but it was punishing the enemy through the hands of the believers
instead of Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل), destroying them or a violent wind.
Now since the Torah(توراة) was revealed; It is Allahسُبحانه وتعالى destroying the enemy with the hands of the believers.
And that is Al-Qital Fee Sabil Lillah(القتال فى سبيل الله)
and that is why the nature of the conflict between
the Ummah(امة) of Musa(موسى) and their enemies is similar to the nature of the conflict between the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ and his enemies.
With the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ, we didn't have a violent wind destroying them or earthquake
even though sometimes Allah would send these miracles but overall, it is through the hands of the believers, the enemy is destroyed.
So there is a similarity in the nature of the conflict.
Number four;
There are two halves of the story of Musa(موسى);
one half is Musa(موسى) and Firaon(فرعون)
and the other half is Musa(موسى) and Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
There are two parts; Both of these are very, very important for us to know.
The part of the conflict between Musa(موسى) and Firaon(فرعون) is very, very important to us
because Firaon(فرعون) is the symbol of tyranny, dictatorship and oppression.
And Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله) we find that, that is the problem that the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ is suffering through.
We have suffered from oppression and tyranny and dictatorship for a very, very long time.
And that's why it is very helpful for us to know the story of Firaon(فرعون).
Because that is something that this Ummah(امة) has suffered from; for a long time; for centuries;
we have suffered oppression and the symbol of oppression and Qur'an is Firaon(فرعون).
So, how can we deal with that oppression?
It is the way that Musa(موسى) have dealt with it.
We learn a lot of experiences from that.
And also Firaon(فرعون) is a king, power through kingdom.
And that is, how Islam is being fought against.
It is through the governments and powers of the throne.
And Dajjal(دجال) is only an extension of that.
Dajjal(دجال) is a king on a throne who will rule over the world.
So that is why the story of Firaon(فرعون) would have a lot of similarities between it and the story of Al-Dajjal(الدجال) .
And then we have the other half of the story of Musa(موسى) is;
Musa(موسى) dealing with his people.
How Musa(موسى) dealt with the Muslim Ummah(امة) of this time; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).?
When you see the faults and the problems of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)
even though they were the Ummah(امة) of Tawheed(تؤحيد), the Ummah(امة) of oneness of Allah.
And you see the faults that we are falling into and getting into.
You see how important it is to know the story of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
In Qur'an su'ar Al-Maida(مائدة); there are Ayaat(آيات), where Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ومن لم يحكم بما أنزل الله فأولئك هم الكافرون۝
فأولئك هم الفاسقون۝
فأولئك هم الظالمون۝
The ones who did not rule according to the book of Allah are the unbelievers;
In other places, it says the corrupt and in other places says the oppressors.
Hudhaifa-bin-Al-Yaman(حديفه بن اليمان) heard some of the tabaein(تابعين) speaking about this and they said;
These Ayaat(آيات) were revealed speaking about Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
He said; Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر), what better cousins to you are the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
Whenever there is something bad in Qur'an; You say; it's speaking about them,
and wherever there's something good in Quran; You say; it's speaking about you.
He wants to teach them a lesson that these Ayaat(آيات) even though they are speaking about Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل),
but whoever is similar to that; from this Ummah(امة) would receive the same punishment.
That is why Allah mentioned it in Qur'an.
If you do not rule over the book of Allah,
whether you are from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) or from any other nation,
that is considered to be kufr(كفر) and it's considered to be dhulm(ظلم) and it's considered to be to fisq(فسق).
Finally, the last reason that I have listed and there are many others.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has talked a lot about Al-Yahood(اليهود).
Because it was in the knowledge of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, who knows everything (Al-Aleem العليم),
that this band of people would be the enemies of the religion of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى from day one, until the Day of Judgment.
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله); the Jews are a very small nation and they have been a very small nation for a very long time.
For centuries, the numbers of the Jews is very limited.
Why didn't Allahسُبحانه وتعالى talk about the Hindus or the Buddhist or the Confucius,
even though there are much more in numbers like He has talked about Al-Yahood(ال يهود)?
Numbers is not the issue;
Al-Yahood(اليهود) from day one, until this day, are the ones who are leading the war and the battle against Islam.
They are the ones who are making the plans and the plots against this religion.
The Yahood(يهود) are the ones, who supported the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين) in the time of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and they are the ones who are supporting the Munafiqeen(مُنافقين) today.
Al-Yahood(اليهود) are the ones who planed together and brought the Ahzaab(احزاب); the Arab tribes together to fight against Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the Jews are the ones who are bringing today the nations of the world against the Muslims.
The Yahood(يهود) are the ones who we're taking care of the word propaganda against Islam.
And the Jews today are the ones, who are taking the lead in the media warfare against Islam.
From day one, they have been the enemies of the religion of Muhammadﷺ,
and they will continue to be the enemies until the last generation of Al-Yahood(اليهود) will be the soldiers and the supporters of the Al- Dajjal(الدجال).
And then it will be the end.
And that's why Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has talked about this nation so that we would know;
وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِأَعْدَائِكُمْ ۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; He is knows best who your enemies are.
The story of Musa(موسى) is very long.
It's a very detailed story, these Ayaat(آيات), or a summary of the story of Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
طسم ۝
تِلْكَ آيَاتُ الْكِتَابِ الْمُبِينِ ۝
نَتْلُو عَلَيْكَ مِن نَّبَإِ مُوسَىٰ وَفِرْعَوْنَ بِالْحَقِّ لِقَوْمٍ يُؤْمِنُونَ۝
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
We recite to you some of the news.
This is News,
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is conveying to you news, of Musa(موسى) and Firaon(فرعون).
The difference between this news and other news that you hear;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that, this news Bil-Haqq(حَقّ); in truth.
Every other piece of news that you hear can be true and can be false.
But this news Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells you; Bil-Haqq(حَقّ), it is the true news.
And, who is this directed to?
لِقَوْمٍ يُؤْمِنُونَ۝
For the believers.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says, and this Ayah(آية) is describing the political and social situation in the time of Musa(موسى).
ان فرعون على فلارض
Firaon(فرعون) exalted himself in the land.
This is the political situation in that time.
Firaon(فرعون) was the only power figure.
And he was so strong and powerful; and he had so much influence over the lives of people, that he thought that he is God.
And he said;
انا ربكم الاعلى
I am your Lord.
And then he said;
وما علمتلكم من اله غيره
I don't know that you have any other God but me.
He has so much power;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given him so much power, that he could get away with this claim and nobody would protest it.
When he said, I am your Lord and I am your God.
Nobody said you're wrong.
He got away with it, because he had so much influence and power over the lives of people.
وجعل أهلها شيعا
He divided the people into parties, and that is how you rule.
Farriq Tasud(فرق تسد);
Divide and Conquer.
He divided the people in Egypt; into different classes, into different tribes.
That is how you dominate by class conflict and by these conflicts in society;
That is how the Kings rule.
And Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were placed on the lowest level; lowest class.
And then he place these other groups from Egypt above them and over them.
So Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) were taking as slaves and servants.
يَسْتَضْعِفُ طَائِفَةً مِّنْهُمْ
He oppressed a group of them which are the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
يُذَبِّحُ أَبْنَاءَهُمْ وَيَسْتَحْيِي نِسَاءَهُمْ ۚ
The children of Israel(اسرائيل) have multiplied a lot.
They started by who?
By Yusuf(يوسف) and his brothers.
But by now, they were already a huge nation;
It says; they were about 600,000 at the time, when Musa(موسى) left with them out of Egypt.
Anyway, Firaon(فرعون) saw a dream; it says that Firaon(فرعون) saw a dream.
In this dream, It was interpreted that there's a child who will be born among the children of Israel(اسرائيل), who will take away your kingdom.
When Firaon(فرعون) heard that interpretation, he said; it's easy, we'll take care of that.
Any child who is born kill him.
So he would kill all of the male children, and he would take the woman as slaves and servants.
وَيَسْتَحْيِي نِسَاءَهُمْ ۚ
So, he kills the sons and he lets the females live.
إِنَّهُ كَانَ مِنَ الْمُفْسِدِينَ۝
He was of those who commit great sins and crimes.
And then Allah says;
وَنُرِيدُ أَن نَّمُنَّ عَلَى الَّذِينَ اسْتُضْعِفُوا فِي الْأَرْضِ
وَنَجْعَلَهُمْ أَئِمَّةً وَنَجْعَلَهُمُ الْوَارِثِينَ۝
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says;
And We wish to do a favor to those who are weak in the land and to make them rulers and to make them the inheritors.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants and Firaon(فرعون) wants, but whatever Allah wills will pass.
Allah wanted to give his favourite to the weak nation.
Allah wanted to bring that weak nation from the bottom and put them on the top.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَنُمَكِّنَ لَهُمْ فِي الْأَرْضِ
And to establish them in the land,
وَنُمَكِّنَ لَهُمْ فِي الْأَرْضِ وَنُرِيَ فِرْعَوْنَ وَهَامَانَ وَجُنُودَهُمَا مِنْهُم مَّا كَانُوا يَحْذَرُونَ۝
And We let Firaon(فرعون) and Haman(هامان) their hosts receive from them that which they feared.
Some of the Sahabah رضى الله عنهم said that, Firaon(فرعون) saw a dream.
He saw a dream where there is a light coming out from the Holy Land, Jerusalem(يروشلم)
and this light or fire والله اعلم swept through Egypt and it destroyed everyone except for the Houses of the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
So he asked for the interpretation of this dream.
He was told that it means that
there will be a man from the children of Israel(اسرائيل) who will take away your kingdom from you;
and will destroy your army and your people.
This was the interpretation of the dream.
So, he said for Firaon(فرعون) it was easy, simple.
He gave his orders to kill every child who was born in the houses Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
And it says that he would send out spies, his security agents, to go and find out any woman of the children of Israel who's pregnant
and they would put her under surveillance before she even gives birth.
And they would put her under surveillance
and as soon as she delivers; if it's a boy, they would slaughter him.
And if it's a girl, they would let her live.
يُذَبِّحُ أَبْنَاءَهُمْ وَيَسْتَحْيِي نِسَاءَهُمْ ۚ
He kills the males and he allows the females live.
The mother of Musa(موسى) became pregnant,
but she concealed her pregnancy.
No matter how strong the security forces and the spying agency is, they are always going to miss something.
There is some information they're going to overlook.
So, in this particular case, in the situation of the mother of Musa(موسى), they did not notice her pregnancy.
So she was able to conceal her pregnancy until she delivered
and when she delivered Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) now it's even more difficult to hide the fact.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told the mother of Musa عليه السلام.
وَأَوْحَيْنَا إِلَىٰ أُمِّ مُوسَىٰ
Now this is not Wahi(وحى) of Nabuwah(نبوة).
The word Wahi(وحى) could mean either inspiration or it could mean revelation to a Nabi(نَبِي).
In this particular situation, it is inspiration; Ilham(الهام).
It is not revelation to a Nabi(نَبِي).
Because when the word Wahi(وحى) is mentioned in Qur'an doesn't necessarily have to mean, revelation of a Nabi(نَبِي)
because, we have a place in Qur'an where Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says in surat-ul-Nahl(سورة النحل);
وَأَوْحَىٰ رَبُّكَ إِلَى النَّحْلِ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We revealed to the bees,
so are the bees prophets.?
So this revelation over here means inspiration.
It's the strongest inspiration in the heart of the mother of Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling her;
وَأَوْحَيْنَا إِلَىٰ أُمِّ مُوسَىٰ أَنْ أَرْضِعِيهِ ۖ
فَإِذَا خِفْتِ عَلَيْهِ فَأَلْقِيهِ فِي الْيَمِّ وَلَا تَخَافِي وَلَا تَحْزَنِي ۖ
إِنَّا رَادُّوهُ إِلَيْكِ وَجَاعِلُوهُ مِنَ الْمُرْسَلِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
And We inspired the mother of Musa(موسى) saying;
Suckle him breastfeed him.
But when you fear for him, then cast him into the river and fear not nor grief.
Now, this is a strong inspiration, because no mother would throw her child in a flowing river.
And for any of you have seen the Nile River, it's a very, very powerful and strong River.
I mean, people who swim there put themselves at risk of drowning; strong swimmers.
Because it's a very violent and strong moving current.
So this is a very strong inspiration;
because no mother would do this; unless, she has a very strong feeling that this is a command from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told her to breastfeed him; breastfeed him as usual.
But whenever you feel danger on him, throw him in what seems to be the biggest danger; the river.
Putting the child in the age of Musa(موسى) might be a few days old;
a baby who can barely see; cannot do himself any good.
And you put him in a river in a wooden box.
That would seem to our limited minds and rational and thinking that, that is throwing him to death.
But because it's an order from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
this righteous mother was able to suppress her strong feelings of motherhood and care for the child
and to trust the child in the hands of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and to believe that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will take care of the child more than her.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in this verse is telling her;
Do not fear nor grief; Don't have fear and don't have grief.
We shall bring him back to you and We will make him one of our messengers.
By the way, this Ayah(آية) it has two do's and don'ts and two pieces of good news.
In this Ayah(آية) there are two orders.
أَرْضِعِيهِ فَإِذَا خِفْتِ عَلَيْهِ فَأَلْقِيهِ فِي الْيَمِّ۝
Breastfeed him; and if you have fear on him, then throw him in the river.
And, this shows you the Bulagha(بلاغه) the beauty of the Qur'an, how in one verse you could have all of these different aspects of language.
So these are two orders;
Breastfeed and throw him or put him in the river.
And then there are two don'ts where it says,
وَلَا تَخَافِي وَلَا تَحْزَنِي ۖ
Don't have any fear and don't have any sorrow.
And then it has two promises in it.
إِنَّا رَادُّوهُ إِلَيْكِ
We will return him unto you.
وَجَاعِلُوهُ مِنَ الْمُرْسَلِينَ۝
And we will make him of the messengers.
So it has two promises to the mother of Musa(موسى); we are going to bring him back to you; Don't worry
and he's going to be of the messengers.
This is a very strong test from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for this righteous mother.
If you care for your child throw him in the river.
So, she breastfed Musa(موسى), she put him in a wooden casket; in a wooden box
and she put him in the Nile River and she let her child go in front of her eyes.
Just to fulfill this inspiration and promise of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
where Allah is telling her; We are going to return him to you and we are going to make him of the messengers.
This mother fulfill the two promises of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى or fulfill the commandment of Allah to receive these promises.
How many promises do we have?
Nevertheless, we're not acting upon the orders of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
We are told that if we're going to strive and struggle in Jihad(جهاد) in the sake of Allah, Allah is going to give us victory.
We're not doing that.
We are told if you spend in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, Allah is going to give you more.
We don't do that.
We are told that if we have tawakul(توكل) in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
Allah is going to provide for us more.
We don't do that.
We are told if we have Taqwa(تقوى) Allah is going to provide us with Rizq(رزق) from sources we don't know.
وَمَن يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَل لَّهُ مَخْرَجًا ۝ وَيَرْزُقْهُ مِنْ حَيْثُ لَا يَحْتَسِبُ
And we don't do that.
The mother of Musa(موسى) did this;
Even though, it is much more difficult for her to do it because she's a mother and this is her child a few days old,
and she was ordered, a drastic and very difficult thing to do.
And that is to put him in the Nile River; But she did it.
And we are going to see the results of her actions.
We're going to see what happens when you fulfill the order of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
We're going to see how Allah fulfills his promises unto you.
When this wooden box was sent in the river; it kept on flowing through the Nile River.
The waves are moving it around.
And there are many houses and communities on this Nile River.
I mean, all of the people of Egypt were living on that river; that was their livelihood.
Egypt is desert, there's no rain.
The people are living on the water of the Nile River.
So that is where all of the communities of Egypt are;
Even until this day; you rarely find communities living on the west or the east flanks of the river; everybody is surrounding this river.
So it is their houses lining up around the Nile River.
This wooden casket is moving.
And out of every house; Out of all of the houses lining up on the west and the east side of the river.
Where does this wooden box choose to park?
All of the people of Egypt are living on this river.
This wooden box is swimming through the waves of the Nile River.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is directing it and guiding it and navigating it through this river.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sends this wooden box right on the shores of the palace of Firaon(فرعون).
The mother of Musa(موسى) threw this child in the Nile River to get him away from Firaon(فرعون).
To get him away from Firaon(فرعون); That's why she put him in the river; in the first place.
So that, the child can run away from Firaon(فرعون);
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants this baby and child to go right to the palace of Firaon(فرعون).
And if the mother of Musa(موسى) was watching this; she's going to say what promise is this?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى promised me that He's going to save my child for me, and then my child goes and parks right next to the palace of Firaon(فرعون)?
But her Eeman(ايمان) was firm.
رَّبَطْنَا عَلَىٰ قَلْبِهَا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We tied her heart firm with Eeman(ايمان).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has a plan.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَالْتَقَطَهُ آلُ فِرْعَوْنَ لِيَكُونَ لَهُمْ عَدُوًّا وَحَزَنًا
This is the plan of Allah; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
Then the household of Firaon(فرعون) picked him up, that he might become for them an enemy and the cause of grief.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has a plan.
Allah wants them To pick up Musa(موسى); so that, he will be grieve for them and he would be their enemy.
And how could that work out; We have no way of understanding.
Because this is a mystery of the omnipotence of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and his Qudrah(قدره).
The Qudrah(قدره) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and His ability.
How could Musa(موسى) end up being the grieve for Firaon(فرعون), when he will be raised up in the palace of Firaon(فرعون)?
So, they picked him up.
What happened is?
Some soldiers or servents; they saw this box; they opened it up; they found the child in there; where did they take it.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants that child not to land in the hands of Firaon(فرعون), but to land in the hands of the wife of Firaon(فرعون); Asiyah(آسيه).
So Asiyah(آسيه) picked up this wooden box and saw this baby in it.
This child, she fell in love with him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put the love of this righteous baby in the heart of this righteous woman.
She said;
وَقَالَتِ امْرَأَتُ فِرْعَوْنَ قُرَّتُ عَيْنٍ لِّي وَلَكَ ۖ لَا تَقْتُلُوهُ
She said; A comfort of the eye for me and for you; kill him not.
So we kind of sense here that, maybe Firaon(فرعون) wanted to kill this child.
Because, the wife of Firaon(فرعون) was saying; Don't kill him.
So maybe there was an attempt to kill Musa(موسى).
I mean, Firaon(فرعون) was killing right and left all of the children of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So he might have felt there's a possibility; this could be from the children of Israel(اسرائيل); why not get rid of him.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put some support for Musa(موسى) in the palace of Firaon(فرعون).
See, when Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants to help His servants;
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ can; You don't know who the soldiers of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى are.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put an insider in the palace of Firaon(فرعون); to support Syedina Musa عليه السلام.
And that is the wife of Firaon(فرعون); She's an insider, she's the queen.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made her a supporter of Musa(موسى).
Just like in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ);
When the non-believers surrounded the Muslims in a Sha'ab(شعب) and they boycotted them for three years.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put in the hearts of some of the strong men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
The intention of breaking up this embargo; even though, they were non Muslims.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can use anyone who wants for the sake of His religion.
Even if, they're non Muslim;
Even if, they intend to be enemies of Islam; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can use their actions against them.
So we should always have trust in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى that no matter how the enemy is strong;
No matter how powerful the devil's work seems to be.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can provide us with victory, if we fulfill the requirements of victory.
إِن تَنصُرُوا اللَّهَ يَنصُرْكُمْ
If you give victory to Allah, Allah will give victory to you.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provide for the helpless child, an insider to take care of him and that is the wife of Firaon(فرعون).
she said;
قُرَّتُ عَيْنٍ لِّي وَلَكَ
He would be comfort for my eyes and comfort for your eyes
and we will take him as an adopted son; Because they did not have any children.
It is said that Firaon(فرعون) said;
قرة عين لك وليس قرة عين لى
He will be a comfort for your eyes but I don't want him to be comfort for mine.
Actually, he's making Dua(دُعَا) against himself.
He said; I don't want this man to be comfort for my eyes.
Let him be comfort for your eyes; And he was comfort for the eyes of Asiyah(آسيه)
but he was not comfort for the eyes of Firaon(فرعون).
So, these words of Firaon(فرعون) were fulfill.
لَا تَقْتُلُوهُ عَسَىٰ أَن يَنفَعَنَا أَوْ نَتَّخِذَهُ وَلَدًا
Don't kill him; Perhaps, he may be a benefit for us or we may adopt him as a son.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأَصْبَحَ فُؤَادُ أُمِّ مُوسَىٰ فَارِغًا ۖ
And the heart of the mother of Musa(موسى) became empty;
Look at the expression, her heart was empty; it was completely drained.
Because she does not have her son in her hands.
She does not know where he is.
Her heart was completely drained.
فَارِغًاۖ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
إِن كَادَتْ لَتُبْدِي بِهِ
She was about to disclose his case.
She was about to go out in the streets of Egypt saying where's my child?
And if she did that; then his case would be exposed,
because it would be known that, he is from the children of Israel(اسرائيل), and he would be killed.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لَوْلَا أَن رَّبَطْنَا عَلَىٰ قَلْبِهَا لِتَكُونَ مِنَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
But we strengthened her heart so that, she might remain as one of the believers.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى strengthen that empty heart with Eeman(ايمان).
Nothing can fill an empty heart; but Eeman(ايمان).
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى filled the heart of the righteous mother of Musa(موسى) with Eeman(ايمان) and that kept her quiet.
She was able to conceal this issue.
She did not speak out about it.
But she told the sister of Musa(موسى); her daughter.
She said; Go and find out, what happened to Musa(موسى)?
When the mother put her baby in the river;
This wooden casket was moving in the Nile River and this sister of Musa(موسى) was following it on the shore.
So, the casket is moving in the river and this girl is running along the river.
So, she knew where the final destination was; She knew that, it was in the Palace of Firaon(فرعون).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not allow Musa(موسى) to suck milk from any breastfeeder.
They brought for him woman to feed him and he would refuse.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not allow Musa(موسى) to drink from anyone.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has a plan.
So now, Musa(موسى) is in the hands of the queen, but he's refusing to suckle any milk.
He does not want to breastfeed.
And then, the sister of Musa(موسى) arrives and she says;
I can provide you with someone who will breastfeed this child.
She's talking about the mother of Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَحَرَّمْنَا عَلَيْهِ الْمَرَاضِعَ مِن قَبْلُ
فَقَالَتْ هَلْ أَدُلُّكُمْ عَلَىٰ أَهْلِ بَيْتٍ يَكْفُلُونَهُ لَكُمْ وَهُمْ لَهُ نَاصِحُونَ۝
And she said to his sister; follow him.
So she; his sister watched him from a far place secretly, while they perceived not.
And we had already forbidden other foster suckling mothers for him.
Until, she said; Shall I direct you to a household who will rear him for you.
And sincerely, they will look after him in a good manner?
They said; Okay, we'll try.
They took the child to the mother of Musa(موسى) and immediately, Musa(موسى) started to breastfeed.
Now, the Queen said; I will want you or I'm inviting you to come and breastfeed him in the palace.
But now, the mother of Musa(موسى) has leverage; She has monopoly over this issue.
Nobody else can breastfeed Musa(موسى); but her.
So, she is setting the terms now.
She said; No, I have husband and I have children; I have to take care of them at home.
So, you have to bring the child to me to my house to breastfeed.
Look at this, Musa(موسى); who was dropped in the river alone; by the mother of Musa(موسى),
because of her Eeman(ايمان);
He is now leaving the Palace of Firaon(فرعون) under Royal Guards and going to the house of his parents
and the mother of Musa(موسى) is being paid to take care of her own child.
وَمَن يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَل لَّهُ مَخْرَجًا۝
The one who has Taqwa(تقوى); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will provide a way out for him.
If the mother of Musa(موسى) did not believe in the promise of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
Her child would have been killed; Musa(موسى) would have been killed.
If the mother of Musa(موسى) kept the child with her; he would have been killed.
But because, she believed in the promise of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and she let him go.
Now, Musa(موسى) is protected by the security guards of Firaon(فرعون).
And he became a source of Rizq(رزق) for the whole family, because they're paying her to take care of Musa(موسى).
And the whole family is honored, because they're taking care of the adopted son of Firaon(فرعون).
Look at the result of Taqwa(تقوى).
This is the result of Taqwa(تقوى).
وَمَن يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَل لَّهُ مَخْرَجًا ۝ وَيَرْزُقْهُ مِنْ حَيْثُ لَا يَحْتَسِبُ ۚ
If you have Taqwa(تقوى), Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is going to provide the way out for you, and he's going to provide for you, from sources you perceive not.
فَرَدَدْنَاهُ إِلَىٰ أُمِّهِ
Who's the one who returned Musa(موسى) to his mother?
Allah.
فَرَدَدْنَاهُ إِلَىٰ أُمِّهِ
So, Did We restore him to his mother?
كَيْ تَقَرَّ عَيْنُهَا وَلَا تَحْزَنَ
That, she might be delighted.
Allah wants her to delight her; Allah wants to make her happy.
And that, she might not grieve.
Allah doesn't want her to grieve.
Why? Because of her righteousness and her Taqwa(تقوى).
وَلِتَعْلَمَ أَنَّ وَعْدَ اللَّهِ حَقٌّ
And so that she might know, that the promise of Allah is true.
وَلَٰكِنَّ أَكْثَرَهُمْ لَا يَعْلَمُونَ۝
But most of them know not.
Most of the people do not know that the promise of Allah is true.
Unfortunately, we all say; we believe in the promise of Allah.
We say that, but it's lip service; Deep in our hearts, we don't act that way.
وَلَٰكِنَّ أَكْثَرَهُمْ لَا يَعْلَمُونَ۝
Most of the people do not know this.
And when Allah says this; it means, they don't act upon that.
They might say that, they believe in the promise of Allah
but who acts upon that and who fulfills these commandments of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to receive the promise of Allah.
I think this part of the story of Musa(موسى);
If we think about it, it is an example of the ultimate level of weakness.
When you depend on Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; no matter how weak you are;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can provide you with the most strength.
Because Bannu Israel(بنو أسرائيل) were helpless and Musa(موسى) was a helpless child.
But the Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided for him protection from all sources.
Our Ummah(امة) is in a similar situation now; we are in a very, very weak state.
If we would put our trust in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, Allah is going to protect us from sources, we perceive not.
Because no way could the mother of Musa(موسى) have imagined; what will happen.
No way, could anyone, decode the plan of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
and understand the mystery of the ability of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and how the plan of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى works.
Musa(موسى) is being raised up in the palace of Firaon(فرعون) and he's receiving the best treatment;
Because he's their adopted son.
Musa(موسى) grew up in the palace of Firaon(فرعون).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَمَّا بَلَغَ أَشُدَّهُ آتَيْنَاهُ حُكْمًا وَعِلْمًا
وَكَذَلِكَ نَجْزِي الْمُحْسِنِينَ۝
And when he attained his full strength and was perfect in manhood, We bestowed on him,
حُكْمًا وَعِلْمًا
Hukum(حكم) is the good and right judgment Ilm(علم) is knowledge.
And we talked about the importance of these two, when we were talking about SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
حُكْمًا وَعِلْمًا
Allah gave the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)  both; not knowledge alone and not the judgment alone.
Allah gave them good judgment and knowledge together, because these two things work together to form the complete personality.
وَكَذَلِكَ نَجْزِي الْمُحْسِنِينَ۝
And thus, do we reward the righteous.
So, Musa(موسى) was described by Rasool Allah ﷺ as being a very large and well built person.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; he was very dark skin, and his hair was curly.
These were the descriptions of Musa(موسى) and he had a very strong presence and personality.
These are the descriptions of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) in the Hadith(حديث).
Musa(موسى) entered into the town; one day.
عَلَىٰ حِينِ غَفْلَةٍ مِّنْ أَهْلِهَا
Allah says; When the people were unaware.
This could have been at noon time or at night time;
The streets were empty; There weren't a lot of people around.
Musa(موسى) saw two men fighting.
And we would see throughout the story of Musa(موسى),
that Musa(موسى) was the type of personality that would not let mistakes pass in front of his eyes, without him intervening.
He had a personality where if, he sees something wrong, he can't let it pass by.
He has to do something; He has to intervene.
So Musa(موسى) saw these two men fighting.
He came to see what's happening.
He saw that one of them, is from his people; the children of Israel(اسرائيل) and the other one was an Egyptian
and they were fighting together.
So Musa(موسى) intervene, to support the Israilite against the Egyptian.
What he did is;
Musa(موسى) had the stick in his hand.
So he pushed the Egyptian with his stick; He just pushed him.
The man fell down; dead.
Musa(موسى) was strong.
Musa(موسى) did not intend to kill; he did not intend to kill.
This was unintentional murder.
But he pushed the man, it was a little bit strong, so the man fell down; dead.
The next day, Musa(موسى) came in the town and he saw the same man from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) fighting with another Egyptian.
The next day, he already picked up another Fight; troublemaker; He's looking for trouble.
Now, Musa(موسى) rushed ahead.
Musa(موسى) this time, when he rushed ahead,
the man from the children of Israel(اسرائيل), thought that Musa(موسى) this time is going to hit him.
So he said, he backed away and he said; Do you want to kill me, like you've killed somebody yesterday?
Until that moment, nobody knew that Musa(موسى) is the one; who killed the Egyptian.
And now this Israelite, leaked the word out in front of the other man, because the other Egyptian was there.
He told Musa(موسى), Do you want to kill me, like you've killed somebody yesterday?
Now, this wasn't a regular or usual homicide; a crime of murder.
This was a big issue.
And it may be headlines all over Egypt.
Because it was a political issue.
Because it was a dispute between an Egyptian and a member of the weak community; Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
The oppressed and the enslaved.
So how can someone from the low class kill someone from the high class?
Because by now, it was already known that Musa(موسى) was from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) as some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say,
but anyway, even if it wasn't the case; it was a big issue.
And it was so big that Firaon(فرعون) and his government met together and his counsel; they met together to discuss this issue.
That is how big it was.
It wasn't an issue that would just go to court; No.
It went all the way up to Firaon(فرعون) and his cabinet and his counsel and they met together to discuss this issue.
Because for them, this was an issue of what? it wasn't Regular murder; it was an issue of terrorism.
It was a terrorist act; That is what this issue was.
Because a Muslim has killed a member of the non Muslim community.
So it's not dealt with the same way they would deal with other crimes which are similar; No.
Because this was committed by a Muslim; It has to be classified as terrorism.
So it was an issue that was discussed by Firaon(فرعون) and his cabinet and the government to fight terrorism through their anti Terrorism Task Force.
So they decided that they have to kill Musa(موسى).
What happened is, that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made this news leak out through one members of the community.
So he came from the other end of town rushing to convey the news to Musa(موسى), and to tell him;
إِنَّ الْمَلَأَ يَأْتَمِرُونَ بِكَ لِيَقْتُلُوكَ
The leaders are making a plan to kill you; So you better leave immediately.
So Musa(موسى) was told afore time, that he will be killed.
I just want to add one thing about this man from Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
When Musa(موسى) saw him causing trouble again, What did he tell him?
He told him;
إِنَّكَ لَغَوِيٌّ مُّبِينٌ۝
He said; you are a plane misleader.
Because, he was causing too much trouble.
When Musa(موسى) told him; you are a plane misleader.
The Israelite interpreted this as Musa(موسى) wanting to attack him.
He thought that Musa(موسى) is going to attack him.
So when Musa(موسى) was moving ahead, he said; you want to kill me just like you have killed someone the day before.
Who did Musa(موسى) help the day before?
He helped this man.
The next day, the man was willing to betray Musa(موسى), who just saved him; the day before.
Musa(موسى) did this man a favor; he helped him and supported him.
The next day this man betrayed Musa(موسى) and disclosed the secret that happened the day before.
This shows you something.
It shows you some of the qualities of people who are humiliated and oppressed.
When people and societies go under oppression and humiliation for a long time;
they become very weak personalities and they become very selfish.
You find that people who are living under oppression, are very selfish people.
If they have been undergoing oppression for a very long time and they do nothing to stop it.
You can find that the reason is because they are selfish.
Everybody's saying; myself!, myself!.
Because if they were considering the community.
The oppression wouldn't continue; they would stop it.
But these people are going through this oppression continuously and suffering the humiliation;
Because they don't want to work together; They are selfish and everyone is looking at his own benefit and gain.
So this man is an example, is a representation of people who are humiliated.
And these are the type of people that Musa(موسى) have had to deal with.
He had to deal with people who lived under the oppression and the tyranny of Firaon(فرعون) for a very, very long time.
See their whole personality; see people when they go under long periods of oppression, they lose dignity.
See this man doesn't have any dignity; He doesn't care if he betrays.
As long as, he's going to save his life; he'll do anything.
They lose the dignity and honor.
And honorable and dignified person is not going to do this to somebody, who did him a favor.
He's going to be grateful and he's willing to die to help Musa(موسى).
He's willing to sacrifice his life to support Musa(موسى) rather than betray Musa(موسى) and cause him all of this suffering and pain.
And that could happen to the Muslim Ummah(امة) today.
If we do not stop the oppression that our Ummah(امة) is going through.
This is the type of personalities that we're going to reap in the end.
Musa(موسى) did not have any time to prepare his belongings and his luggage; He had to immediately flee out of Egypt.
And he headed east; That's the way to get out.
And he immediately rushed out of Egypt.
There was no time to do anything, because the warrant for his arrest was already out.
So he had to leave immediately.
So he left out of Egypt to the direction of the east.
And he traveled all the way; out of Egypt.
It is said that; he had shoes on; He kept on walking, until his shoes were torn apart.
And then he was walking on his barefoot, until his skin peeled out.
And he would eat whatever he would find.
He was eating the leaves of the trees until, the surrounding his lips was a green layer;
Because of the dryness and the harshness of the leaves of trees; It came out from his mouth.
And he was alone with no food, no supporter, no friends, no family and he kept on walking to the east.
Because he doesn't know; how far he needs to move to get out of Egypt.
Until he arrived to an area called Madyan(مَدْيَن).
Musa(موسى) is continuing out, he's just marching out of Egypt.
He reached to this area called Madyan(مَدْيَن);
And there were some wells in that area; Abar(ابر); There's some water.
There were men picking up water, drinking for themselves, feeding their goats and their camels.
But then there were two women on the side, who had their sheep with them and they cannot drink any water.
Keep in mind that Musa(موسى) is exhausted; tired from a long trip.
The skin of his feet is peeled out; It is not time to intervene and help anyone.
But because the personality of Musa(موسى) would not let any mistake pass by.
He wanted to see why these two women are not drinking?
So he walked up to them; And he said; What is the matter with you?
They said; We cannot drink until these men leave.
Because these men are pushing each other and fighting next to the water and everyone is getting water out by the strength of his muscle.
How can these two women go and fight with them?
Now Musa(موسى); who's exhausted and tired; can barely walk.
He went in and he fought with these men
and he pushed them aside and he brought out a few buckets of water.
He provided it for the two women and for their sheep.
And then Musa(موسى) could not handle it any further, he went and he laid down under a tree; completely exhausted.
So he went down under a tree.
And he said;
رَبِّ إِنِّي لِمَا أَنزَلْتَ إِلَيَّ مِنْ خَيْرٍ فَقِيرٌ۝
He said; Oh Allah, I am in need of any good that you can send down on me.
Musa(موسى) was broke, he had nothing.
So, he's telling Allahسُبحانه وتعالى anything, anything that you can give me, I need it, in this moment.
إِنِّي لِمَا أَنزَلْتَ إِلَيَّ مِنْ خَيْرٍ فَقِير۝
Oh Allah, whatever you're going to bestow on me; I need it.
Musa(موسى) is making this Dua(دُعَا) and before the Dua(دُعَا) is over, the help of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was already on its way.
The Dua(دُعَا) has not done yet; And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is already sending the help to the direction of Musa(موسى).
Who came and met Musa(موسى) under the tree?
It was one of the women whom he supported.
She came to Musa(موسى) and said;
فَجَاءَتْهُ إِحْدَاهُمَا تَمْشِي عَلَى اسْتِحْيَاءٍ
قَالَتْ إِنَّ أَبِي يَدْعُوكَ لِيَجْزِيَكَ أَجْرَ مَا سَقَيْتَ لَنَا ۚ
Then there came to him one of the two women walking shyly.
She said; verily my father calls you that, he may reward you for having watered for us.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
عَلَى اسْتِحْيَاءٍ
She was walking with Hayah(حياء); She had shyness.
Shyness; Hayah(حياء) is a quality that men and women, in the West have lost.
By the way Hayah(حياء) is not only for women; It's for men and women.
We know that Sayidina Uthman Ibn Affanرضى الله عنه, was described as a man who has a lot of Hayah(حياء).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ would sit in a certain way and represent himself to Uthman Ibn Affan(عثمان ابن عفان) in a certain way
and when he was asked, Why don't you do that with Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر).?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Shouldn't I be shy from a man who the angels are shy from?
So this is not the quality only for women; It's also for men Hayah(حياء); shyness is a branch of Eeman(ايمان).
شعبه من شعب الايمان
This woman came to Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) walking very shy.
Shy, because she's dealing with an alien or foreign man.
She doesn't know him; She was shy.
The Muslim sister, she came.
تَمْشِي عَلَى اسْتِحْيَاءٍ
Walking with shyness.
She said; My father wants to pay you; reward you, for what you have done.
So, Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) followed her.
Some of the Salaf(سلف) say that, Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) walked in front of her.
Anyway, they reached there to meet this old man.
He's old because the woman said;
وَأَبُونَا شَيْخٌ كَبِيرٌ۝
In the Ayah(آية) it says; our father is old; He's an old man.
So Musa(موسى) went to visit this old man.
Some of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) and actually many of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) say that, this man was Syedina Shoaibعليه الصلواة والسلام.
There is no evidence to support that from Qur'an or from Sunnah(سنة).
But there is a strong opinion among many of the scholars of Tafseer(تفسير) of the Salaf(سلف).
They say that, he was Syedina Shoaib(سيدنا شُعَيب).
So Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) went and met with him.
فَلَمَّا قَصَّ عَلَيْهِ الْقَصَصَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; So Musa(موسى) started narrating his story;
Telling him the story of his life; It's a very interesting story.
And Musa(موسى) started narrating that story to this old man.
فَلَمَّا جَاءَهُ وَقَصَّ عَلَيْهِ الْقَصَصَ قَالَ لَا تَخَفْ ۖ نَجَوْتَ مِنَ الْقَوْمِ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
When Musa(موسى) mentioned his story to the old man, the old man told him;
Do not fear; You are now safe from the oppressor people.
He's telling him; you have crossed the border; You're out of Egypt now.
So don't worry, it's safe for you over here;
He was in Madyan(مَدْيَن).
Syedina Musaعليه السلام when he left from Egypt.
He didn't know where he's going; He never traveled out of Egypt.
He just walked toward the east trying to get out of Egypt.
And now this man is telling him; you have crossed the border and now you have reached to safety.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; You have escaped from the people who are Dhualimeen(ظالمين); the oppressors.
This daughter; she went to her father and she gave him a wonderful advice.
She told him; Oh my father! hire him.
قَالَتْ إِحْدَاهُمَا يَا أَبَتِ اسْتَأْجِرْهُ ۖ
And one of them said; Oh my father! hire him.
And she gave the reasons; why you should hire him.
What did she say?
They said that this woman was very wise; What did she say?
إِنَّ خَيْرَ مَنِ اسْتَأْجَرْتَ الْقَوِيُّ الْأَمِينُ۝
The best man to hire is the strong and the trustworthy.
These are two qualities you want to search for; in the employer.
Strength and trustworthiness.
What does strength mean? Quwwah(قوة); Qawi(قوى); he's strong.
This is relevant to the kind of job that will be done.
If it is a physically demanding job, then the strength means strong in his physical body.
If it's an intellectual kind of job, then you need to be strong in your mind.
To summarize it; you need to be very strong in your field.
That is what is meant by Qawi(قوى); strong.
Al-Amin(الامين); Trustworthy.
It's not enough to be strong.
Because you could be strong but you're using your strengths against your organization.
You could be using it for your own benefit and harming the others.
So you have to be trustworthy too.
And that's why Abu Bakrرضى الله عنه, when he appointed Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) to be the Khalifah(خليفه);
he told the Muslims, why he appointed him?
He said; The best man to appoint on you is Al-Qawwi(القوى), Al-Amin(الامين);
The strong and The trustworthy.
They learn their rules from Qur'an.
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) did not go through any political science classes or degrees.
He learned the politics of Islam from Qur'an.
So when he wanted to hire somebody or to appoint somebody to the position of Khilafah(خِلَافَه);
He has a whole generation of Sahaba(صحابه) in front of his eyes; All of them are righteous.
Righteousness is common among all of the Sahabah(صحابه).
So, how can you choose among them?
He looked for these two qualities: Quwwah(قوة) and Amanah(امانه); Strength and Trustworthiness.
So, the father offered the job to Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى),
but he went a little further; he took another step.
He also offered Musa(موسى) one of his daughters.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ إِنِّىٓ أُرِيدُ أَنْ أُنكِحَكَ إِحْدَى ٱبْنَتَىَّ هَٰتَيْنِ عَلَىٰٓ
عَلَىٰٓ أَن تَأْجُرَنِى ثَمَٰنِىَ حِجَجٍۢ ۖ
فَإِنْ أَتْمَمْتَ عَشْرًا فَمِنْ عِندِكَ ۖ
وَمَآ أُرِيدُ أَنْ أَشُقَّ عَلَيْكَ ۚ
سَتَجِدُنِىٓ إِن شَآءَ ٱللَّهُ مِنَ ٱلصَّٰلِحِينَ۝
He said; I intend to wed you one of these two daughters of mine; on condition that you serve me for eight years,
but if you complete 10; it would be a favor from you.
But I intend not to place you under a difficulty; If Allah will; you will find me one of the righteous.
So, he said; I will marry you one of my daughters; what is the Maher(مهر) that you will pay me?
You work for me for eight years.
And if you want to complete 10 years, that's up to you; It's not part of our agreement.
But I would suggest it; if you want to work for 10 years, that will be better.
But the bottom line is you have to work for minimum of eight.
Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) to make it clear, he said;
قَالَ ذَٰلِكَ بَيْنِي وَبَيْنَكَ ۖ
أَيَّمَا الْأَجَلَيْنِ قَضَيْتُ فَلَا عُدْوَانَ عَلَيَّ ۖ وَاللَّهُ عَلَىٰ مَا نَقُولُ وَكِيلٌ۝
Musa(موسى) wanted to be clear about this agreement.
He said, that is a settled deal between me and you,
whichever of the two terms I fulfill, there will be no injustice to me, and Allah is surety over what we say.
Musa(موسى) is saying; If I work for eight years; Don't blame me; Don't commit any injustice to me.
The agreement is that, I work for eight years with you.
Rasool Allah ﷺ asked Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل); which of the two terms that Musa(موسى) fulfill?
Did he work for eight or did he work for ten?
Jibreelعليه السلام  told Muhammadﷺ ;
اتمها واكملها
That he worked for the best and the most complete, and that is ten years.
This is the Ihsaan(احسان) and Itqan(اتقان) perfection of your work, even though the agreement was clear that, I have to work for eight years.
But he completed it and he worked for ten.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تسليما كثيرا